<writtenanswers>
<image src="S5CV0001P0I0627"/>
<col>1223</col>
<title>QUESTIONS ANSWERED IN WRITING.</title>
<date format="1909-03-01"></date>
<section>
<title>Rosyth Dockyard.</title>
<p><member>Mr. HOLT</member> asked the First Lord of the Admiralty what part of the works at Rosyth is being constructed of granite; whether alternative tenders were obtained for constructing such part in concrete; and, if so, what was the comparative cost?</p>
<col>1224</col>
<p><member>Mr. M'KENNA</member>: It is not easy to specify briefly where granite is used: it may be said generally that it is used in copings, altars, bilge and keel blocks, and quoins to cassion steps. No alternative tenders were obtained for substituting concrete for granite, as granite was considered to be necessary in the places where it is to be used.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Summary Jurisdiction Act, 1879.</title>
<p><member>Mr. LLOYD MORGAN</member> asked the Home Secretary if he will say how many people over 16 years of age were in 1907, or for the last year for which statistics are available, convicted in England and Wales of misdemeanours other than those specified in the second column to the First Schedule of the Summary Jurisdiction Act, 1879, as subsequently extended; and how many of these were sentenced to imprisonment for six months or less?</p>
<p><member>Mr. GLADSTONE</member>: The following information will perhaps meet my hon. Friend's wishes: In the year 1907, 5,764 persons over 16 years of age were convicted in England and Wales of indictable offences other than those specified in the second column of the First Schedule to the Summary Jurisdiction Act, 1879, as subsequently extended, and 2,492 of these were sentenced to imprisonment for six months or less.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Floods in Ireland (Bann and Barrow Areas).</title>
<p><member>Mr. MOORE</member> asked the Chancellor of the Exchequer if he is prepared to make any grant for works or other measures to relieve the flooding in the Bann area?</p>
<p>The hon. Member further asked if the right hon. Gentleman was prepared to make any grant for works or other measures to relieve the flooding in the Barrow area; and, if so, under what head in the Votes?</p>
<p><member>Mr. LLOYD-GEORGE</member>: As at present advised, I am unable to hold out any hope of a Government grant for the purposes referred to in the hon. Member's questions.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Public Elementary Schools (Corporal Punishment).</title>
<p><member>Mr. GEORGE GREENWOOD</member> asked the President of the Board of Education if he will say how many cases of corporal punishment of boys, girls, and infants respectively occurred in the public elementary schools in London, Liverpool, Manchester, Bristol, Leeds, and Sheffield during 1908?</p>
<p>Mr. RUNCIMAN: I regret I have noinformation on this matter.</p>
</section>
</writtenanswers>
