<writtenanswers>
  <image src="S6CV0089P0I0719"/>
  <col>1</col>
  <title>Written Answers to Questions</title>
  <date format="1985-12-16">Monday 16 December 1985</date>
  <group>
    <title>AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD</title>
    <section>
      <title>Food Storage</title>
      <body>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04896">Mr. Canavan asked the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food what is his latest available information on the amount of surplus food stored <i>(a)</i> in the United Kingdom and <i>(b)</i> in the European Economic Community and the costs of storage.</p>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04897"><member>Mr. Gummer</member>: A note setting out the volume of United Kingdom and Community</p>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04898">The storage, handling and related costs of United Kingdom intervention </p>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Cereal Stocks</title>
      <body>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04899">Mr. Pike asked the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food what proportion of the total cereal production in intervention in the United Kingdom has been stored for more than one year.</p>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04900"><member>Mr. Gummer</member>: Twenty nine per cent. of the grain held at 29 November 1985 has been in store for more than one year.</p>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Veterinary Services</title>
      <body>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04901">Mr. Maxwell-Hyslop asked the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food whether he will make a statement about the restructuring of veterinary investigation centres and their management.</p>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04902"><member>Mr. Jopling</member>: I have carefully considered the proposals for restructuring of veterinary investigation centres in the light of the many comments received from interested organisations and individuals. In addition, we have undertaken a detailed investment 'appraisal of the recommendations made by the efficiency study.</p>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04903">Against this background, I have concluded that the Gloucester centre should be closed but with retention of the badger-tuberculosis unit. I confirm that Chester and Cardiff centres will be closed. Discussions on the future of the Moulton centre have taken place with Northampton county council to ascertain whether it would wish to take it over. It concluded that it did not wish to do so. Accordingly this centre will also be closed. I have also decided that it would be wrong to close both the Leeds and Lincoln centres, which would leave the large pig population in the area without adequate laboratory diagnostic facilities, and concluded that the best course would be to retain and enlarge the Lincoln centre and close that at Leeds. This represents a better option than establishing a new centre in the area.</p>
        <col>2</col>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04904">On further examination it is clear that closure of Truro, Starcross, Winchester and Wye centres with their replacement by two new centres would not be cost effective. I have therefore decided not to take any action in relation to these centres. The timing of the closures will require careful consideration and this is now being pursued with a view to implementation during the first half of next year.</p>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-04905">Finally, I confirm that we shall be establishing a new and more centralised management structure for the veterinary investigations which I am confident will increase efficiency and enable the more effective deployment of available resources.</p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </group>
  <group>
    <title>ENVIRONMENT</title>
    <section>
      <title>Building Controls (Inner London)</title>
      <body>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-05004">Mr. Maples asked the Secretary of State for the Environment when he proposes to lay regulations to apply the system of building controls currently operating in England and Wales to inner London.</p>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-05005"><member>Mr. John Patten</member>: My right hon. Friend has today laid before Parliament the Building (Inner London) Regulations 1985. It is intended that the regulations will come into operation on 6 January 1986. The effect of the regulations is that the building control system will become essentially the same in inner London as in the rest of England and Wales. With certain limited exceptions the Building Regulations 1985 will apply to building work in inner London in place of the present constructional byelaws made under the London Building Acts. The Building (Approved Inspectors, etc) Regulations 1985 will also apply to inner London from 6 January 1986.</p>
        <col>14</col>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-05006">The Greater London council and the district surveyor service will be responsible for administering the new system for inner London until 1 April 1986, when responsibility for this function will pass to the inner London borough councils and the Corporation of the City of London.</p>
        <p id="S6CV0089P0-05007">The regulations provide for transitional arrangements so that schemes in progress on the 6 January will continue to be subject to the London Building Acts and byelaws.</p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </group>
  <group>
    <section>
      <title>TRINIDAD (RAILWAY COMMITTEE).</title>
      <body>
        <p id="S5CV0193P0-00512"><member>Mr. SPOOR</member> asked the Secretary of State for the Colonies whether he is aware that the Governor of Trinidad</p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </group>
</writtenanswers>
