<housecommons>
<image src="S5CV0643P0I0817"/>
<col>1619</col>
<title>HOUSE OF COMMONS</title>
<date format="1961-07-06">Thursday, 6th July, 1961</date>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04691" align="center"><i>The House met at half-past Two o'clock</i></p>
<debates>
<section>
<title>PRAYERS</title>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04692" align="center">[Mr. SPEAKER <i>in the Chair</i>]</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>PRIVATE BUSINESS</title>
<section>
<title>SUTTON COLDFIELD CORPORATION<lb/> BILL [Lords]</title>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04693"><i>Read the Third time and passed, with Amendments.</i></p>
</section>
<section>
<title>CITY OF LONDON (VARIOUS POWERS)<lb/> BILL [Lords]</title>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04694"><i>As amended, considered; to be read the Third time.</i></p>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>PETITION</title>
<section>
<title>Land Titles, Kenya</title>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04695"><member>Mr. F. Harris</member><membercontribution>: I beg to present a Petition. Because of my known personal associations with Kenya, I have been requested by Kenya landowners, holding freehold or leasehold grants under the provisions of the Crown Lands Ordinance, 1915, to present to the House of Commons this Petition with over 3,800 signatures. Against each signature details are given of the property held. I understand that this is the first Petition which settlers of a British Colony have found it necessary to submit to the House of Commons.<lb/>
The Petitioners state how they originally came into possession of their titles granted by the Governor of Kenya on behalf of Her Majesty the Queen and her predecessors. Many of the Petitioners were encouraged by the British Government to settle in Kenya under the Discharged Soldiers' Settlement Scheme at the termination of the 1914&#x2013;18 war, and others emigrated to Kenya under the auspices of the European Agricultural Settlement Board established by the Kenya Government.<lb/>
The Petitioners explain how they have spent considerable sums in developing their property and this has now resulted in a European agricultural investment alone in Kenya exceeding &#x00A3;70 million. This investment has been made in reli
<col>1620</col>
ance upon the continuing validity of titles granted by the Crown and the ability of Her Majesty's Government to maintain peace and good order in the Colony.<lb/>
It is recognised that Kenya will eventually become an independent State under African majority rule. On numerous occasions African political leaders have been asked their intentions in recognising the validity of titles of land and property once independence has been granted, but as yet, regrettably, no satisfactory assurances have been given. Such lack of confidence arising has made European property virtually unsaleable and considerable hardship is being caused, including hardship to widows and old people who cannot dispose of their property. Furthermore, the present titles are no longer regarded as security by banks and other financial concerns. It is felt that such property may be confiscated by a future Government without any or adequate compensation, and all this has, unfortunately, meant the slowing down of agricultural development to the detriment of all peoples in Kenya, with a serious effect on Kenya's economy, which can unhappily be seen in increased unemployment affecting all races, particularly Africans.<lb/>
This Petition has been beautifully prepared, and I hope that hon. Members will take the opportunity of seeing it at the Journal Office.<lb/>
The Petition concludes with the Prayer
<quote>that such proper and immediate steps are taken in the premises as will remedy the present lack of confidence in land titles which is causing untold harm to the economy of this Colony and Protectorate and to the welfare of its peoples and in particular
<ol>
<li>(<i>a</i>) that it be acknowledged that responsibility for such titles rests with Her Majesty's Government;</li>
<li>(<i>b</i>) that in pursuance of such responsibility immediate steps be taken to restore the confidence of title holders by firm and effective guarantees for compensation in the event of expropriation whether by sequestration or by circumstances which render the quiet enjoyment of such titles no longer possible;</li>
<li>(<i>c</i>) that in the case of such title holders who wish to dispose of their assets urgent steps are taken to restore free negotiability in land so that such land may be acquired, utilised and developed in the interests of the general economy of the said Colony and Protectorate.</li></ol></quote>
<quote>And your Petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray, etc.</quote></membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04696"><i>To lie upon the Table.</i></p>
</section>
</section>
<oralquestions>
<image src="S5CV0643P0I0818"/>
<col>1621</col>
<title>ORAL ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS</title>
<section>
<title>HIGH COMMISSION<lb/> TERRITORIES</title>
<section>
<title>Morse Mission (Recommendations)</title>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04697">1. <member>Mr. Wan</member><membercontribution> asked the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations whether he will make a statement about the implementation of the recommendations of the Morse Report on the development of the High Commission Territories.</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04698">5. <member>Mr. G. M. Thomson</member><membercontribution> asked the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations if he is now in a position to make a statement on the extent to which the Government intends to carry out the recommendations of the Morse Commission Report on the High Commission Territories; and if he will give details of the financing of these plans.</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04699"><member>The Under-Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations (Mr. Bernard Braine)</member><membercontribution>: The Morse Mission, in its Report, recommended further development in the three High Commission Territories under the main heads of roads, agriculture, including animal husbandry and education, and in Bechuanaland, water supplies, additional to the work already proceeding in these fields with substantial assistance from Colonial Development and Welfare funds. The Mission recognised that its recommendations could only be put into effect over a period of years<lb/>
To enable a start to be made with implementing the Mission's recommendations and further development in the field of education, authority is being given to the High Commissioner to incur additional development expenditure up to &#x00A3;1.2 million in the period ending 31st March, 1963, above that already authorised under the Colonial Development and Welfare Act, 1959. This authorisation means that the High Commissioner will dispose of nearly &#x00A3;6 million in all from now to March, 1963, for work on existing schemes and the commencement of new ones.<lb/>
There is also the possibility of finance from the International Development Association and other international organisations.</membercontribution></p>
<col>1622</col>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04700"><member>Mr. Wall</member><membercontribution>: While I welcome my hon. Friend's statement, may I ask whether the Morse Mission recommendation about Roma University is included in the sums which he mentioned? Secondly, how much money has been made available in total to the High Commission Territories for development over a period of five years from, say, 1959?</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04701"><member>Mr. Braine</member><membercontribution>: I should prefer my hon. Friend to put down a Question about the first point. The answer to the second question is that, including the unspent allocations from the previous Act, the sum is over &#x00A3;9 million.</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04702"><member>Mr. Thomson</member><membercontribution>: While I welcome the fact that the Government have at last decided to make a start with the Morse recommendations, is the Minister aware that this is a very modest start? Is he aware that the Morse recommendations suggested that there should be not &#x00A3;1.2 million of capital development but &#x00A3;7 million of capital development very quickly and then &#x00A3;500,000 a year of recurrent expenditure for five years? Do the Government intend to go ahead to accept the Morse recommendations in their entirety as the very minimum necessary to put the High Commission Territories on a decent economic basis?</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04703"><member>Mr. Braine</member><membercontribution>: As the hon. Member knows, we have to take account of our serious balance of payments position and the other heavy calls upon our resources, but I am confident that the total sum-likely to be available to the Territories from all sources will be enough to enable them to undertake or make progress with all the development projects within their physical capacity. As for the details, I am in consultation with the High Commissioner as to the projects which are most urgent at present.</membercontribution></p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Development Adviser</title>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04704">7. <member>Mr. Marquand</member><membercontribution> asked the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations whether he will appoint a development officer of wide experience in Africa to superintend the development projects which are planned for Basutoland, Bechuanaland and Swaziland.</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04705"><member>Mr. Braine</member><membercontribution>: As was stated in reply to a Question by my hon. Friend the Member for Reading (Mr. Emery) on 28th July last, Sir Gordon Hadow. who
<image src="S5CV0643P0I0819"/>
<col>1623</col>
was a member of the Morse Mission, and had previously had wide experience in administration in West Africa, holds the appointment of Development Adviser to the High Commissioner for Basutoland, the Bechuanaland Protectorate and Swaziland.</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04706"><member>Mr. Marquand</member><membercontribution>: May we take it that this appointment means that the Government have the intention of making the development of the three High Commission Territories an operation which the whole world can see as an operation shop window, as someone has called it? Does it mean that, although it is nearly eighteen months since the Morse Mission presented its Report, the Government intend to make a really good thing of this, something for which the whole world can admire this country?</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04707"><member>Mr. Braine</member><membercontribution>: My right hon. Friend has had the benefit of the advice of this able and experienced administrator during the period which the right hon. Gentleman has mentioned. However, I should have thought that the Answer which I gave to the first Question on the Order Paper is the answer to his supplementary question.</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04708"><member>Mr. Emery</member><membercontribution>: Would my hon. Friend state that, as well as making this operation a shop window, it should be really worth while in its development for all of the Territories? Can he say whether any international finance, particularly from the International Development Association, might be used towards this end?</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04709"><member>Mr. Braine</member><membercontribution>: The answer to the first part of my hon. Friend's supplementary question is "Yes". With regard to the second part, I referred to the possibility of finance from the International Development Association, which recently sent a mission to the High Commission Territories to examine the possibility of a loan for road construction. We are also in touch with such organisations as the United Nations International Children's Emergency Fund, the World Health Organisation and the United Nations Special Fund, which is at present considering applications made to it by the Bechuanaland Protectorate for a preliminary survey of the Okavango Swamps in the north-western corner of the Territory and a hydrological survey of river water sources over the whole of the Territory.</membercontribution></p>
<col>1624</col>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04710"><member>Mr. Marquand</member><membercontribution>: The hon. Gentleman's Answer to the earlier Question was very disappointing. It implied that the Government were prepared only to continue with a small instalment of the Morse development plan. Would not he agree that there is no project of economic development in the whole of Africa more important at present than this one? Will he indicate that the Government intend over a period of years to carry through all the recommendations in the Morse Report?</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04711"><member>Mr. Braine</member><membercontribution>: This new money will enable the High Commissioner to supplement the development plans which are already in existence. The right hon. Gentleman must not suggest that development plans are not already under way. As a matter of fact, the allocation of &#x00A3;6-75 million to the three Territories under the Colonial Development and Welfare Act, 1959, was not enough to carry out these plans in full. Therefore, a large part of the new money will be devoted to this purpose.</membercontribution></p>
</section>
<section>
<title>SWAZILAND</title>
<section>
<title>Education</title>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04712">2. <member>Mr. Brockway</member><membercontribution> asked the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations what decisions have been made on African education in Swaziland, following the termination of education facilities in the Union of South Africa: and if these decisions include the inauguration of inter-racial schools at all levels with equal opportunities for African and European children.</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04713"><member>Mr. Braine</member><membercontribution>: The education facilities provided for Swazi students by South African authorities have been access to South African universities, and the right to take public examinations set by the Joint Matriculation Board of the University of South Africa. The former facility was withdrawn in 1959 except in regard to the Natal Medical School.<lb/>
Suitably qualified Swazi students can now receive university education at either Pius XII College at Roma in Basutoland, the University College of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, or at universities overseas.<lb/>
The latter facility is still provided, but as I informed the hon. Gentleman in
<image src="S5CV0643P0I0820"/>
<col>1625</col>
reply to his Question on 29th June, facilities are also provided for African and other pupils to take the London Overseas General Certificate of Education.<lb/>
In regard to inter-racial schools, as I stated in reply to a Question by the hon. Member for Dundee, East (Mr. G. M. Thomson) on 29th June, the Swaziland education authorities are examining how these can best be introduced.</membercontribution></p>
<p id="S5CV0643P0-04714"><member>Mr. Brockway</member><membercontribution>: Does not the termination of the arrangements with the Union of South Africa give an opportunity for a new start in education in Swaziland, not only in higher education but in primary education, too? Is the Minister aware that there is segregation in the schools of Swaziland and that only &#x00A3;5 a year per head is spent on the African child compared with &#x00A3;90 on the European child? Will he do something to establish free inter-racial compulsory education for all the children in Swaziland?</membercontribution></p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</oralquestions>
</debates>
</housecommons>
