<houselords>
<image src="S5LV0238P0I0089"/>
<col>167</col>
<title>HOUSE OF LORDS</title>
<date format="1962-03-14">Wednesday, 14th March, 1962</date>
<p id="S5LV0238P0-00409">The House met at half past two of the clock, The LORD CHANCELLOR on the Woolsack.</p>
<debates>
<section>
<col>170</col>
<title>LONDON GOVERNMENT</title>
<p id="S5LV0238P0-00634"><member>LORD MORRISON OF LAMBETH</member><membercontribution>: I do not know whether I can persuade my noble friend Lord Montgomery of Alamein to come and vote with us, or whether the pattern of uniformity that he has learnt as a result of his visits to certain countries abroad has so eaten into his mind that he thinks, "How nice it is to see a Tory Government following the example of the countries behind the Iron Curtain!"<lb/>
Now I do not know what is going to happen. I would remind your Lordships that this is a free assembly. The other place cannot be as free as we are, because the House of Commons can bring down the Government, and they have constituencies. But noble Lords are perfectly entitled to vote on the merits of the question, and are not bound to
<image src="S5LV0238P0I0157"/>
<col>303</col>
vote merely out of a sense of loyalty to the Government or to the Central Conservative Office. I should hope that your Lordships would put this great capital city before the Party political considerations which obviously affect the Government in this matter. Therefore, we shall go to a Division, and we trust that your Lordships will vote in favour of the Motion which I have had the honour to move. We have had a useful day. As I say, we have had the best of the debate. We clearly did in the other</membercontribution></p>
<division>
<table type="span">
<tr>
<td colspan="3" align="center"><b>CONTENTS</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Addison, V.</td>
<td>Kenswood, L.</td>
<td>Nathan, L.</td>
</tr>
</table>
<table type="span">
<tr>
<td colspan="3" align="center"><b>NOT-CONTENTS</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ailwyn, L.</td>
<td>Derwent, L.</td>
<td>Milverton, L.</td>
</tr>
</table>
</division>
<p id="S5LV0238P0-00635">Resolved in the negative, and Motion disagreed to accordingly.</p>
<col>304</col>
<p id="S5LV0238P0-00636">place as well&#x2014;and, my goodness!, we certainly did on the London County Council. The truth is that the promoters of this conspiracy against democracy have not got a leg to stand on, and the sooner they fall over themselves and meet themselves coming back, the better it will be.</p>
<p id="S5LV0238P0-00637">On Question, Whether the said Motion shall be agreed to?</p>
<p id="S5LV0238P0-00638">Their Lordships divided: Contents, 3; Not-Contents, 3.</p>
<p id="S5LV0238P0-00639">House adjourned at thirteen minutes before ten o'clock.</p>
</section>
</debates>
</houselords>
