<writtenanswers>
<image src="S6CV0089P0I0719"/>
<col>1</col>
<title>Written Answers to Questions</title>
<date format="1985-12-16">Monday 16 December 1985</date>
<group>
<title>AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD</title>
<section>
<title>Food Storage</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04896">Mr. Canavan asked the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food what is his latest available information on the amount of surplus food stored <i>(a)</i> in the United Kingdom and <i>(b)</i> in the European Economic Community and the costs of storage.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04897"><member>Mr. Gummer</member>: A note setting out the volume of United Kingdom and Community intervention stocks, including those of foodstuffs, on the latest available dates is deposited in the Library of the House and is updated monthly.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04898">The storage, handling and related costs of United Kingdom intervention products (including barley and feedwheat) in 1984 were &#x00A3;46&#x00B7;4 million. We have no figures for storage costs incurred by other member states.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Cereal Stocks</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04899">Mr. Pike asked the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food what proportion of the total cereal production in intervention in the United Kingdom has been stored for more than one year.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04900"><member>Mr. Gummer</member>: Twenty nine per cent. of the grain held at 29 November 1985 has been in store for more than one year.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Veterinary Services</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04901">Mr. Maxwell-Hyslop asked the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food whether he will make a statement about the restructuring of veterinary investigation centres and their management.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04902"><member>Mr. Jopling</member>: I have carefully considered the proposals for restructuring of veterinary investigation centres in the light of the many comments received from interested organisations and individuals. In addition, we have undertaken a detailed investment 'appraisal of the recommendations made by the efficiency study.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04903">Against this background, I have concluded that the Gloucester centre should be closed but with retention of the badger-tuberculosis unit. I confirm that Chester and Cardiff centres will be closed. Discussions on the future of the Moulton centre have taken place with Northampton county council to ascertain whether it would wish to take it over. It concluded that it did not wish to do so. Accordingly this centre will also be closed. I have also decided that it would be wrong to close both the Leeds and Lincoln centres, which would leave the large pig population in the area without adequate laboratory diagnostic facilities, and concluded that the best course would be to retain and enlarge the Lincoln centre and close that at Leeds. This represents a better option than establishing a new centre in the area.</p>
<col>2</col>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04904">On further examination it is clear that closure of Truro, Starcross, Winchester and Wye centres with their replacement by two new centres would not be cost effective. I have therefore decided not to take any action in relation to these centres. The timing of the closures will require careful consideration and this is now being pursued with a view to implementation during the first half of next year.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04905">Finally, I confirm that we shall be establishing a new and more centralised management structure for the veterinary investigations which I am confident will increase efficiency and enable the more effective deployment of available resources.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Less-productive Areas</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04906">Mr. Barry Jones asked the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food if he will outline his policy concerning the effect of the European Economic Community common agricultural policy on the more extensive systems for poorer land; and if he has considered alternative crops and systems for the less productive areas of the United Kingdom.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04907"><member>Mrs. Fenner </member><i>[pursuant to her reply,</i> 13 December 1985]: Our policy for the areas of poorer land in the United Kingdom is to take full advantage of the provisions of EC Directive 75/268 on farming in less favoured areas. Accordingly, we secured agreement in Brussels last year to a major extension of these areas which now represent over 50 per cent. of our agricultural land. For many years we have paid headage allowances in them and on 28 November my right hon. Friend the Minister announced an increase in the rates. Within the constraints of the common agricultural policy we are continually seeking ways of assisting these areas. But most of them are riot basically suitable for any form of agricultural production except livestock rearing. It is partly with this in mind that in the new agricultural improvement scheme, introduced on 1 October, we included certain new features to encourage conservationally sensitive investments and diversification.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Crop Research</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04908">Mr. Barry Jones asked the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food if he proposes to advise the Agriculture and Food Research Council that it should invest in research on a broader range of crops; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04909"><member>Mrs. Fenner </member><i>[pursuant to her reply,</i> 13 December 1985]: The Agricultural and Food Research Council already studies a wide range of crops. There is close collaboration between my Department and the council in order to identify opportunities for the further development of agriculture.</p>
</body>
</section>
</group>
<group>
<title>ATTORNEY-GENERAL</title>
<section>
<title>Legal Aid</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04910">Mr. John Fraser asked the Attorney-General if it is the intention that the scheme of interim payment on account of costs under the legal aid scheme should again he made in the current financial year; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<image src="S6CV0089P0I0720"/>
<col>3</col>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04911"><member>The Solicitor-General</member>: Yes. Another payment on account scheme will operate in the current financial year, on a similar basis to those operated in each of the last two years.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Magistrates</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04912">Mr. Hoyle asked the Attorney-General if he will enumerate magistrates in England and Wales under the following categories: <i>(a)</i> sex, <i>(b)</i> age groupings, <i>(c)</i> occupation, <i>(d)</i> social background, <i>(e)</i> resident or nonresident within their petty sessional area and <i>(f)</i> if they have acknowledged a political viewpoint, party affiliation.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04913"><member>The Solicitor-General</member>: On the last count at the beginning of the year there were 27,244 active justices of the peace, of which 15,980 were male and 11,264 female. The other information could not be ascertained except at undue cost.</p>
</body>
</section>
</group>
<group>
<title>PRIME MINISTER</title>
<section>
<title>Honours List</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04914">Mr. Dalyell asked the Prime Minister (1) what procedure is followed by Departments in submitting names for the honours list; and if she will move to appoint a joint committee to review the present departmental procedure with the object of widening its scope;
<ol>
<li>(2) if she will define the phrase political services as it is used by her in submitting her list for honours;</li>
<li>(3) what representations she has received on the procedure followed by Departments in submitting names for the honours list; and what reply she has sent;</li>
<li>(4) if she has any plans for reviewing and modernising the departmental machinery for the submitting of names for honours lists; and if she will make a statement;</li>
<li>(5) what are the functions and powers of the political honours scrutiny committee in relation to the suitability of individuals whose names are proposed to be submitted for honours to Her Majesty;</li>
<li>(6) on what dates the political honours scrutiny committee met in each of the last five years;</li>
<li>(7) who are the current members of the political honours scrutiny committee; and what are the criteria for making appointments to the committee;</li>
<li>(8) what criteria are used in determining whether an individual's name should be included on the list of proposed honours submitted to the political honours scrutiny committee;</li>
<li>(9) how many names were included in the list of proposed honours submitted to the political honours scrutiny committee in each of the last five years; and if she will provide a breakdown according to the political parties in respect of which those names were submitted.</li>
</ol></p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04915"><member>The Prime Minister</member>: It has rightly been the practice of successive Prime Ministers not to disclose or discuss details of the procedures and processes by which their recommendations to the Crown for inclusion in honours lists are arrived at, and I do not propose to depart from that practice.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04916">I keep the arrangements under regular review, and they are modified from time to time in the light of changing needs or circumstances. I have no plans for any kind of external review.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<col>4</col>
<title>Strategic Defence Initiative</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04917">Mr. Dalyell asked the Prime Minister what scientific advice she sought from outside the Government about the feasibility of the strategic defence initiative programme before Her Majesty's Government concluded an agreement with the United States Administration on research projects; and if she will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04918"><member>The Prime Minister</member>: None. The United States strategic defence initiative is a research programme to investigate the feasibility of strategic defence.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>British Atlantic Committee</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04919">Mr. Nellist asked the Prime Minister what was the financial support given by the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation in each of the last 10 years to the British Atlantic committee.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04920"><member>The Prime Minister</member>: The British Atlantic committee (BAC), whom we have consulted, receives no grant from the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation. NATO refund a proportion of the travelling costs of visits to NATO headquarters organised by the BAC and other voluntary associations affiliated to the Atlantic Treaty Association. In the case of the BAC, this amounted to &#x00A3;13,201&#x00B7;50 in 1984&#x2013;85.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Anglo-Irish Agreement</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04921">Sir John Biggs-Davison asked the Prime Minister if, having regard to the international status of the Anglo-Irish agreement, she will require a Minister at the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, or other appropriate representatives of that Department, to attend meetings of the Inter-Governmental Council.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04922"><member>The Prime Minister</member>: Membership of the conference is small and flexible. The Foreign and Commonwealth Office will be represented as appropriate.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04923">Sir John Biggs-Davison asked the Prime Minister which Ministers and Departments of State have taken part or been represented in meetings of, and within the framework of, the Anglo-Irish Intergovernmental Council.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04924"><member>The Prime Minister</member>: My right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, my hon. Friends the Minister of State, Northern Ireland Office, and the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State attended the first meeting of the intergovernmental conference on 11 December. The Northern Ireland Office and Foreign and Commonwealth Office were represented at official level. There have been no other meetings.</p>
</body>
</section>
</group>
<group>
<title>HOME DEPARTMENT</title>
<section>
<title>Prisoners (Petitions)</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04925">Mr. Tom Cox asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department what has been the number of petitions received by his Department from prisoners in prisons in England and Wales in each of the last five years.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04926"><member>Mr. Mellor</member>: As I stated in reply to a question from the hon. Member for Knowsley, North (Mr. Kilroy-Silk) on 30 October at column <i>556,</i> no record is kept of the total number of petitions received from prisoners in prison in England and Wales.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<image src="S6CV0089P0I0721"/>
<col>5</col>
<title>Advancement of Women</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04927">Ms. Harman asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department whether he will establish law reform committees constituted as proposed in paragraph 66 of the United Nations Nairobi forward looking strategies for women.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04928"><member>Mr. Waddington</member>: My right hon. Friend has no plans to do so. Every Government Department already has a duty to keep under review as appropriate the legislation relevant to its areas of responsibility. The Equal Opportunities Commission has a duty to keep under review the working of the Sex Discrimination Act 1975 and the Equal Pay Act 1970 and may review other legislation in the fulfilment of its other statutory duties.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04929">Ms. Harman asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department if he will establish a special office within his Department to monitor periodically and accelerate the process of equitable representation of women as called for in paragraph 88 of the United Nations Nairobi forward looking strategies for women.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04930"><member>Mr. Waddington</member>: The Home Office designated two equal opportunity officers in January 1984. They oversee and monitor the equal opportunities policy within the Departments, including the Civil Service programme of action for women.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04931">Ms. Harman asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department what steps he is taking to evaluate those parts of the United Nations forward looking strategies for women which apply to his Department; what resources he has allocated to this; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04932"><member>Mr. Waddington</member>: Those parts of the 'forward looking strategies' which are relevant to the Home Office are being carefully considered as part of the normal work of the Department.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Departmental Appointments</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04933">Ms. Harman asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department if he will list those bodies to which his Department makes appointments, the number of appointees and the number of these who are women.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04934"><member>Mr. Hurd</member>: The information is contained in the Cabinet Office publication "Public Bodies 1984". I understand that the 1985 edition is to be published on 17 December and that a copy will be placed in the Library.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Pit Bull Terriers</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04935">Mr. Greenway asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department if he will take steps to secure the removal from the United Kingdom of two pit bull terriers recently imported from the United States of America and currently in quarantine.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04936"><member>Mr. Mellor</member>: The Government have no power to remove from the United Kingdom animals which have been legally imported and properly held in compliance with our quarantine regulations.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Foreign Visitors</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04937">Mr. Chris Smith asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department what records and statistics are compiled of the number of United States citizens entering Britain each year.</p>
<col>6</col>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04938"><member>Mr. Waddington</member>: Nationals of all countries outside the European Community are required on entering the United Kingdom to complete a landing card which includes details of the purpose of their journey. Analyses of these cards showing the numbers admitted by nationality (including the United States of America) and purpose of journey are published annually in table 1 of "Control of Immigration: Statistics, United Kingdom" (Cmnd. 9544 for 1984).</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>National Drugs Unit</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04939">Sir Eldon Griffiths asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department (1) whether the establishments of forces from which officers are to be seconded to the national drugs co-ordinating units are to be increased so as to enable additional officers to be recruited to replace them;</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04940">(2) if the police officers being seconded to the national drugs unit under the command of Mr. Colin Hewitt are to be placed on central service.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04941"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: For the period of their service in the national drugs intelligence unit (NDIU), provincial officers are seconded to the Metropolitan police. They do not remain on the strength of their home force and chief officers providing officers to NDIU may replace them for the duration of that secondment; there is thus no need for any increase in establishment. NDIU is funded as a common police service.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04942">This reply also provides information pursuant to my reply of 13 December to a question from my hon. Friend about police officers being seconded to the NDIU.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04943">Mr. Mason asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department what progress has been made in establishing a new national drugs intelligence unit and the creation of drug wings within regional crime squads; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04944"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: The national drugs intelligence unit, superceding the central drugs intelligence unit, came formally into existence on 1 November. It currently consists of 25 officers drawn from provincial forces as well as from the Metropolitan police together with five officers from Her Majesty's Customs and Excise and 16 civilian staff.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04945">My right hon. Friend has indicated to police authorities his readiness to approve appropriate increases in establishments of regional crime squads, to make provision for drugs wings, which they are currently considering.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04946">Mr. Mason asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department what is the estimated extra annual expenditure to the South Yorkshire police committee and the metropolitan council in the funding of the new drug wings within regional crime squads; to what extent this will be nationally funded; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04947"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: The precise arrangements for the funding of each regional crime squad, including drugs wings, are a matter for its constituent police authorities. Eligible expenditure will rank for 50 per cent. police grant from the Home Office in the usual way.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04948">Mr. Mason asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department whether he will meet a delegation from the Association of Metropolitan Authorities to discuss the operational and financial implications of establishing drug
<image src="S6CV0089P0I0722"/>
<col>7</col>
wings within each regional crime squad and the possibilities of national funding; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04949"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: As the then Home Secretary indicated, we are ready to approve requests for increases in regional crime squad establishments necessary to create drugs wings. The extra expenditure involved will qualify for 50 per cent. police grant from the Home Office in the usual way. Moreover, specific provision has been made in police grant related expenditure to cover local authority expenditure for this purpose.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04950">The addition of drugs wings will not change the operational or other arrangements as regards the control of regional crime squads.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04951">Officials are already in touch with the AMA, and my right hon. Friend is ready to consider any particular issues which it may wish to raise: but we hope that police authorities will play their part in the tripartite system by recognising in financial provision the priority which the Government attaches to the investigation of drugs offences.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Prisoners (Statistics)</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04952">Mr. Cohen asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department if he will list, for the most recent week for which the data can be conveniently assembled, the number and percentage of prisoners in each closed prison and in aggregate who spent more than 18 hours a day <i>(a)</i> in their cells on three or more days, <i>(b)</i> on average and (c) on any day.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04953"><member>Mr. Mellor</member>: This information is not available centrally and could only be obtained at disproportionate cost.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reward Payments</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04954">Mr. Cohen asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department what is the policy of the Metropolitan police towards reward payments; in what circumstances they may be made; what guidance or limits are laid down regarding their size; at what level the decisions to sanction payments are made; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04955"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: The Commissioner of Police does not disclose details of reward payments. The policy is that payments are made in suitable cases, where there is no risk of compromising the criminal process. They vary in size but the decision is always taken at the highest level within the specialist Operations Department.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Civil Defence</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04956">Mr. D. E. Thomas asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department (1) whether the pilot study in home defence region 10 examining the need and scope for improved co-ordination of home defence planning takes into account the transition to war measures contained in the United States-United Kingdom lines of communication agreement;</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04957">(2) if he will place in the Library a copy of the interim report of the pilot study concerning the co-ordination of planning in home defence region 10; and when the final report is expected.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04958"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: This study is expected to be complete in a year or so's time after which the results will be made available to the House. An internal report has been made
<col>8</col>
on the first part of the study which has confirmed the need for regional co-ordination. It would not be appropriate to place it in the Library. The study takes into account the agreement referred to in as much as plans made under it bear on regional co-ordination.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Detained Young Persons</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04959">Mr. Dalyell asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department what estimate he has as to how many persons under the age of 16 years were detained in the penal system in England and Wales at the latest date for which figures are conveniently available.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04960"><member>Mr. Mellor</member>: According to the records held centrally, which are approximate, on 31 October 1985 about 340 persons aged under 16 were held in prison department establishments in England and Wales.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Cinemas (Safety) Regulations 1985</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04961">Mr. Alfred Morris asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department when he now expects to issue the Cinemas (Safety) Regulations 1985 and accompanying guidance; if he has agreed to any changes to the draft regulations as originally circulated; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04962"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: It is planned both to make the Cinemas (Safety) Regulations and issue the accompanying guidance during the course of 1986. No significant changes to the draft regulations are expected, but the guidance's advice on access for disabled people will be revised on the lines explained in the reply given on 5 December 1985 to a question from my hon. Friend the Member for Exeter (Mr. Hannam).</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Freemasons</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04963">Mr. Hoyle asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department what records justices' clerks keep of persons in their area known to be freemasons.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04964"><member>Mr. Mellor</member>: None.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Citizenship</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04965">Mr. Madden asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department if he will make it his policy not to place any impediment in the way of people claiming British citizenship by descent being able to exercise their rights, including rights of appeal, in the same way as Momotaj Begum, the daughter of Nurul-Islam, a British citizen settled here with his wife and other children, following the recent decision of the immigration appeal tribunal in this case.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04966"><member>Mr. Waddington</member>: British citizens do not require leave to enter the United Kingdom under the Immigration Act 1971. The immigration officer's examination of such persons is confined to establishing that they are British citizens. The tribunal determination to which the hon. Member refers concerns rights of appeal, not substantive questions of admission. Passengers who are refused entry because they do not satisfy the. immigration officer that they qualify under the Immigration Act and the rules but who nevertheless can put forward a claim to British citizenship by descent may, as the tribunal confirmed, appeal against refusal on the grounds that they do not need leave to enter.</p>
<image src="S6CV0089P0I0723"/>
<col>9</col>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04967">In the Government's view passengers claiming to be British citizens by descent have such a right of appeal only if there appears to be some basis for the claim. The instructions available to immigration officers cover the matters set out above.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04968">The Government have no immediate proposals for changes in the operation of the immigration control. They do, however, keep these arrangements under continuous re-examination and would not hesitate to take appropriate action if attempts were made to misuse the tribunal's determination to evade the prescribed entry clearance procedures overseas.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Emergencies</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04969">Mr. Corbett asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department what steps he is taking to ensure adequate co-operation in dealing with peacetime emergencies between local authorities, emergency services, public services and voluntary bodies.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04970"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: This is already covered in sections 22&#x2013;25 of the "Emergency Planning Guidance to Local Authorities" issued last June. A copy is in the Library.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04971">Mr. Corbett asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department (1) if he will estimate total spending by local authorities on training, designation and preparation of appropriate staff at each level to cope with peacetime emergencies;</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04972">(2) what, in each of the past five years, has been the level of <i>(a)</i> central Government and <i>(b)</i> local authority spending on planning for non-nuclear emergencies.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04973"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: This information is not available in the form requested.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04974">Mr. Corbett asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department if he will list the categories of grant available to local authorities for planning to deal with peacetime emergencies.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04975"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: None is available to local authorities specifically to support peacetime emergency planning.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Immigration</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04976">Mr. Dalyell asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department (1) what statistics are collected by immigration service officers serving terminal 3 at Heathrow airport regarding right hon. and hon. Members' representations in respect of arriving passengers refused admission by immigration officers there; and if he will publish the statistics collected regarding the first nine months of the current year;</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04977">(2) what is his policy towards the collecting of statistics at ports of arrival of the number of immigration cases attracting representations by right hon. and hon. Members; what analyses are carried out of these statistics <i>(a)</i> at the ports of arrival and <i>(b)</i> elsewhere; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04978"><member>Mr. Waddington</member>: At all ports, the number of cases in which a right hon. or hon. Member makes representations is recorded. At terminal 3 Heathrow in the first nine months of this year it is recorded that representations by right hon. or hon. Members were made in about 2,500 cases. These statistics are required as management information both at the ports, and centrally, as a record of the cases themselves, and as a measurement of the work
<col>10</col>
involved and of the resource implications of that work. The available information is looked at in a variety of ways depending on the issue being examined.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04979">Mr. Dalyell asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department (1) pursuant to the answer of 2 December, <i>Official Report,</i> column <i>26,</i> if he will place in the Library any statistical data submitted by the Immigration Service Union in support of its concern expressed at the increase in the number of immigration cases attracting representations from right hon. and hon. Members; and if he will make a statement;</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04980">(2) what is his policy towards members of the immigration service gathering statistics on the number of immigration cases attracting representations by right hon. and hon. Members for union purposes; and if he will make a statement;</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04981">(3) what information he has disclosed to representatives of immigration service officers about the number of immigration cases attracting representations by right hon. and hon. Members; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04982"><member>Mr. Waddington</member>: The statistics available to me of the number of representations made by right hon. and hon. Members about immigration cases are compiled and presented by immigration service management and/or by my private office. I have not received such statistics from representatives of the Immigration Service Union but, in my discussion with it, both I, and it, referred to the considerable increase this year in cases attracting such representations at the ports.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Metropolitan Police</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04983">Mr. Stuart Holland asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department how many South African or former Rhodesian nationals have been recruited to the Metropolitan police; in what years; and in which divisions.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04984"><member>Mr. Giles Shaw</member>: The Commissioner of Police of the Metropolis informs me that the information requested is as follows:
<table>
<tr>
<td colspan="3" align="center"><i>Officers of South African origin</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><i>Rank</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Year of joining police service</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Currently serving at</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chief Inspector</td>
<td align="right">1963</td>
<td align="right">S District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chief Inspector</td>
<td align="right">1972</td>
<td align="right">A3 Branch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Inspector</td>
<td align="right">1967</td>
<td align="right">N District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Inspector</td>
<td align="right">1973</td>
<td align="right">N District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1959</td>
<td align="right">C11 Branch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1963</td>
<td align="right">W District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1968</td>
<td align="right">Special Branch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1971</td>
<td align="right">M District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1976</td>
<td align="right">L District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1977</td>
<td align="right">K District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1978</td>
<td align="right">C District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1979</td>
<td align="right">P District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1979</td>
<td align="right">S District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1962</td>
<td align="right">Special Branch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1974</td>
<td align="right">C District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1975</td>
<td align="right">R District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1976</td>
<td align="right">C District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1976</td>
<td align="right">Special Branch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1976</td>
<td align="right">D District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1977</td>
<td align="right">Royalty and Diplomatic Protection Department</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1981</td>
<td align="right">P District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1981</td>
<td align="right">Q District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1981</td>
<td align="right">M District</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
<image src="S6CV0089P0I0724"/>
<col>11</col>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04985"><table>
<tr>
<td><i>Rank</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Year of joining police service</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Currently serving at</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">B District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">E District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">F District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">D District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">I District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1984</td>
<td align="right">P District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1984</td>
<td align="right">Y District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1985</td>
<td align="right">Z District</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04986"><table>
<tr>
<td colspan="3" align="right"><i>Officers of Rhodesian origin</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><i>Rank</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Year of joining police service</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Currently serving at</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Inspector</td>
<td align="right">1974</td>
<td align="right">B8 Branch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1976</td>
<td align="right">W District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sergeant</td>
<td align="right">1979</td>
<td align="right">B District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1972</td>
<td align="right">T District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1977</td>
<td align="right">M District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1977</td>
<td align="right">X District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1979</td>
<td align="right">A District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1979</td>
<td align="right">G District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1980</td>
<td align="right">X District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1980</td>
<td align="right">A District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1980</td>
<td align="right">N District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1980</td>
<td align="right">Y District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1981</td>
<td align="right">Y District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1981</td>
<td align="right">M District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1981</td>
<td align="right">G District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1981</td>
<td align="right">Q District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1981</td>
<td align="right">Y District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">B District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">K District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">E District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">P District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">N District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">M District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">G District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1982</td>
<td align="right">E District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1983</td>
<td align="right">A District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1983</td>
<td align="right">Q District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1983</td>
<td align="right">T District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1983</td>
<td align="right">C District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1983</td>
<td align="right">P District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1983</td>
<td align="right">J District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1984</td>
<td align="right">M District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1984</td>
<td align="right">A District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1984</td>
<td align="right">Y District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1985</td>
<td align="right">H District</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Constable</td>
<td align="right">1985</td>
<td align="right">B District</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Local Government Reform</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04987">Mr. Fatchett asked the Secretary of State for the Home Department if he will give separately for the six metropolitan county councils and for the Greater London council, the number of civil servants working in his Department on duties associated with the implementation of the Local Government Act 1985, listing in each case the numbers and ranks of officers and the estimated cost per year of each group.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04988"><member>Mr. Hurd</member>: No staff are presently engaged exclusively on such work. The total estimated staff time devoted to reorganisation in all seven areas is:
<table>
<tr>
<td><i>Grade</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Total staff input at each grade devoted to this work</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 3</td>
<td align="right">0&#x00B7;2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 4</td>
<td align="right">less than 0&#x00B7;1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grade 5</td>
<td align="right">1&#x00B7;0</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
<col>12</col>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04989"><table>
<tr>
<td><i>Grade</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Total staff input at each grade devoted to this work</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Senior legal assistant</td>
<td align="right">less than 0&#x00B7;1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Principal (and related specialists)</td>
<td align="right">3&#x00B7;4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SEO (and equivalents)</td>
<td align="right">1&#x00B7;4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Junior administrators (HEO/HEO(D)/EO/AT)</td>
<td align="right">3&#x00B7;4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Clerical grades (CO/CA)</td>
<td align="right">0&#x00B7;3</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04990">The estimated annual cost is &#x00A3;213,000. About &#x00A3;13,300 can be attributed to work on Greater London but it is not possible to provide any further breakdown by area. The figures do not include members of Home Office inspectorates who are consulted on reorganisation preparations.</p>
</body>
</section>
</group>
<group>
<title>ENVIRONMENT</title>
<section>
<title>Water</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04991">Mr. Chris Smith asked the Secretary of State for the Environment why, under article 20 of the European Community directive (80/778/EC) relating to the quality of water intended for human consumption, he has applied for a delay on lead for four years and on all private water supplies for 10 years for the United Kingdom as a whole, rather than specified geographical areas thereof.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04992"><member>Mr. John Patten</member>: The Government's response of 1983 to the ninth report of the Royal Commission on environmental pollution set a target date of December 1989 for reducing lead concentrations in drinking water to acceptable levels. Our application to the European Commission under article 20, which is consistent with that policy, relates to Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland and to the areas covered by the Anglian, Severn-Trent, North West and Yorkshire water authorities where major improvement programmes are still under way. These programmes will be substantially complete by the target date.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04993">Private supplies, although only serving 1 per cent. of the population, are spread throughout the country and in general do not constitute a serious health risk. District councils have a duty to ascertain the wholesomeness of private water supplies and powers to ensure that action is taken to secure improvement when necessary. The article 20 application does not relate to private supplies serving more than 500 people.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Z Scores</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04994">Mr. Hargreaves asked the Secretary of State for the Environment if he is satisfied that the statistical technique known as Z scores used by his Department accurately reflects the poverty, deprivation and difficulties within each local authority.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04995"><member>Sir George Young</member>: There is no single authoritative measure of the difficulties faced by a particular area. The Z scores prepared by my Department provide a comparative index of local authority areas, combining six indicators of deprivation based on information at census enumeration district level. They provide a useful guide to the incidence of multiple deprivation, but cannot give a comprehensive picture of an area's social and economic circumstances.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<image src="S6CV0089P0I0725"/>
<col>13</col>
<title>Retail Superstore Developments</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04996">Mr. Ashdown asked the Secretary of State for the Environment what emphasis he places on the anticipated employment potential of large retail superstore developments when assessing an appeal through referred planning applications; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04997"><member>Mr. Tracey</member>: Each case must be considered on its merits in the light of all the circumstances.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>GLC (Land and Property)</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04998">Mr. Wheeler asked the Secretary of State for the Environment what information he has as to the total amount of land and property in the possession of the Greater London council; and what is the latest estimate of its value.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-04999"><member>Mr. Tracey</member>: My Department does not have comprehensive information about the GLC's land and property holdings. It is for successor authorities to obtain information about the property to be transferred to them at abolition.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Holiday Project Funding</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05000">Ms. Harman asked the Secretary of State for the Environment what he plans to spend on holiday project funding from the traditional urban programme in 1986&#x2013;87; and if he proposes to restore the &#x00A3;400,000 initially cut from the current year's funding.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05001"><member>Sir George Young</member>: Bids from local authorities are being considered and an announcement will be made in the new year.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Thermal Insulation Standards (Building Regulations)</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05002">Mr. Speller asked the Secretary of State for the Environment if he will increase the thermal insulation standards of the building regulations in energy efficiency year.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05003"><member>Sir George Young</member>: The requirements of the regulations, including those for thermal insulation, are under review. The principal aim of the review is to reduce the burden of regulation, but the Government recognise that the building regulations have a role in setting basic standards of cost-effective energy efficiency.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Building Controls (Inner London)</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05004">Mr. Maples asked the Secretary of State for the Environment when he proposes to lay regulations to apply the system of building controls currently operating in England and Wales to inner London.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05005"><member>Mr. John Patten</member>: My right hon. Friend has today laid before Parliament the Building (Inner London) Regulations 1985. It is intended that the regulations will come into operation on 6 January 1986. The effect of the regulations is that the building control system will become essentially the same in inner London as in the rest of England and Wales. With certain limited exceptions the Building Regulations 1985 will apply to building work in inner London in place of the present constructional byelaws made under the London Building Acts. The Building (Approved Inspectors, etc) Regulations 1985 will also apply to inner London from 6 January 1986.</p>
<col>14</col>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05006">The Greater London council and the district surveyor service will be responsible for administering the new system for inner London until 1 April 1986, when responsibility for this function will pass to the inner London borough councils and the Corporation of the City of London.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05007">The regulations provide for transitional arrangements so that schemes in progress on the 6 January will continue to be subject to the London Building Acts and byelaws.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05008">Dr. David Clark asked the Secretary of State for the Environment if he will list, with dates, the orders made under section 29 of the Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05009"><member>Mr. Waldegrave</member>: My right hon. Friends the Secretaries of State for Wales and for Scotland are responsible for making section 29 orders within their own territories. In total, the following orders have been made:&#x2014;
<table>
<tr>
<td><i>Order</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Date Made</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Baddesley Common (Hampshire) Nature Conservation Order 1982</td>
<td align="right">21 October 1982</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Sandford Heath (Dorset) Nature Conservation Order 1982</td>
<td align="right">9 December 1982</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Tealham and Tadham Moors (Somerset) Nature Conservation Order 1983</td>
<td align="right">23 March 1983</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Annesley Woodhouse Quarry (Nottinghamshire) Nature Conservation Order 1983</td>
<td align="right">24 June 1983</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Waltham Chase Meadows (Hampshire) Nature Conservation Order 1983</td>
<td align="right">28 June 1983</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Carstairs Kames (Strathclyde) Nature Conservation Order 1984</td>
<td align="right">31 May 1984</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Carnkief Pond (Cornwall) Nature Conservation Order 1984</td>
<td align="right">21 September 1984</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The West Westray (Orkney) Nature Conservation Order 1984</td>
<td align="right">26 September 1984</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Tan-y-Gadair, Cadair Idris (Gwynedd) Nature Conservation Order 1984</td>
<td align="right">2 October 1984</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Uddens Heath (Dorset) Nature Conservation Order 1984</td>
<td align="right">22 October 1984</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Llyn Mawr (Powys) Nature Conservation Order 1984</td>
<td align="right">3 December 1984</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Walton Moss (Cumbria) Nature Conservation Order 1984</td>
<td align="right">20 December 1984</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Horse Field (North Yorkshire) Nature Conservation Order 1984</td>
<td align="right">21 December 1984</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Upton Heath (Dorset) Nature Conservation Order 1985</td>
<td align="right">22 January 1985</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Leek Moors (Staffordshire) Nature Conservation Order 1985</td>
<td align="right">1 May 1985</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Tealham and Tadham Moors (Somerset) Nature Conservation Order 1985</td>
<td align="right">7 April 1985</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The West Mersea Meadow (Essex) Nature Conservation Order 1985</td>
<td align="right">17 May 1985</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Hencott Pool (Shropshire) Nature Conservation Order 1985</td>
<td align="right">17 July 1985</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Coedydd A Chorsydd Aber Teifi (Dyfed)</td>
<td align="right">6 August 1985</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05010">Dr. David Clark asked the Secretary of State for the Environment if he will provide details, including dates, of those orders under section 29 of the Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981 which were proposed by the Nature Conservancy Council and which he rejected.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05011"><member>Mr. Waldegrave</member>: In three cases submitted to him by the Nature Conservancy Council, my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for the Environment was not satisfied
<image src="S6CV0089P0I0726"/>
<col>15</col>
that the criteria set out in section 29 of the Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981 had been fully met. Details of the three sites are:
<table>
<tr>
<td><i>Sire</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Date rejected</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>Comment</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Went Ings&#x2014;South Yorkshire</td>
<td align="right">30 August 1983</td>
<td align="right">Order requested to avert damage. Agreement involving exchange of land subsequently reached.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sherburn Willows&#x2014;North Yorkshire</td>
<td align="right">8 February 1985</td>
<td align="right">Order requested to curtail damage. Modified site being renotified.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Brimham Rocks&#x2014;North Yorkshire</td>
<td align="right">27 February 1985</td>
<td align="right">Order requested to avert damage. Site currently protected under the provisions of section 28 of the Act.</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Local Government Reform</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05012">Mr. Fatchett asked the Secretary of State for the Environment if he will list separately for <i>(a)</i> the six metropolitan county councils and <i>(b)</i> the Greater London council, the number of civil servants working in his Department on duties associated with the implementation of the Local Government Act 1985, listing in each case the numbers and ranks of officers and the estimated cost per year of each group.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05013"><member>Mr. Tracey</member>: I will answer this question shortly.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Channel Fixed Link</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05014">Sir Hector Monro asked the Secretary of State for the Environment if he will make it his policy to consult the Nature Conservancy Council on all relevant environmental and nature conservation matters before Her Majesty's Government come to a decision on the preferred route for a Channel fixed link; and if he will make a statement.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05015"><member>Mrs. Rumbold</member>: Yes. The Government have consulted the Nature Conservancy Council on the relevant environmental and nature conservation matters in respect of the proposed Channel fixed link and will take its views into account in reaching a decision on which (if any) scheme is to be preferred.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sewer Collapse (North-West)</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05016">Mr. Nicholas Winterton asked the Secretary of State for the Environment (1) what was the extent of sewer collapse in the north-west region in each of the last three years for which figures are available; and how this figure compares with the average for the other regions in each of those years;</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05017">(2) what percentage of total United Kingdom sewer collapse occurred in the north-west region in each of the last five years for which figures are available.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05018"><member>Mr. John Patten</member>: The North West water authority reported 690, 690 and 600 significant collapses respectively in 1981&#x2013;82, 1982&#x2013;83 and 1983&#x2013;84. Reporting standards have improved but they vary between water authorities and this makes comparisons unreliable. Ignoring those variations, the north west has about 14 per cent. of the collapses in England and Wales. The rate of collapses per kilometre is about the same as for England and Wales as a whole.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<col>16</col>
<title>Housing Statistics</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05019">Mr. Nicholas Winterton asked the Secretary of State for the Environment what information he has concerning the ratio of housing stock to inhabitants in each of the member countries of the European Economic Community.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05020"><member>Sir George Young</member>: I will write to my hon. Friend as soon as possible with the information available.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05021">Mr. Nicholas Winterton asked the Secretary of State for the Environment what was the crude surplus by which the number of dwellings in England and Wales exceeded the number of households in the latest year for which figures are available; and how this figure compares with the adjusted figure, taking into account second homes, unfit dwellings, unoccupied dwellings undergoing repair and concealed households.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05022"><member>Sir George Young</member>: 1981 is the most recent year for which information is available about each of the items referred to in the question. The "crude surplus" of dwellings over households in England and Wales was:
<table>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"><i>Number</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dwellings</td>
<td align="right">19,086,000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Households</td>
<td align="right">18,293,000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>"Crude surplus"</td>
<td align="right">793,000</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05023">There is no unique conventional set of adjustments to be made to the crude surplus. The 1981 figures for the item referred to in the question are:
<table>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"><i>Number</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Second residences, including holiday accommodation</td>
<td align="right">221,000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dwellings that were vacant and undergoing improvement</td>
<td align="right">181,000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unfit dwellings</td>
<td align="right">1,207,000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Concealed families</td>
<td align="right">343,000</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05024">Some of the concealed families are likely to have lived that way from choice. There is probably some overlap between vacant dwellings undergoing improvement and unfit dwellings. Many of the unfit dwellings could prabably be made fit by remedial work.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>London Forum</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05025">Mr. Sheerman asked the Secretary of State for the Environment if he will give approval to the funding which has been allocated by the Greater London council for the London Forum.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05026"><member>Mr. Tracey</member>: I am not aware of any application by the GLC for consent in respect of a payment to London Forum.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Easiform Houses</title>
<body>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05027">Mr. Sumberg asked the Secretary of State for the Environment what information he has about the number of Easiform houses which <i>(a)</i> have been reported as defective and <i>(b)</i> have been reported as in good repair.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05028"><member>Mr. John Patten</member>: Over 60,000 Easiform houses are estimated to have been built in England and Wales. A preliminary analysis of local authorities' responses to my Department's recent stock condition inquiry has identified only some 38,000 houses of this type; and that authorities had some information on 36,500. Some 1,000 were reported to require no renovation work of any kind; the
<image src="S6CV0089P0I0727"/>
<col>17</col>
other 35,500 were said to require renovation work averaging &#x00A3;5,100 per house, compared with an average cost of &#x00A3;4,900 for all dwellings requiring renovation.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05029">Mr. Sumberg asked the Secretary of State for the Environment how many representations he has received from hon. Members seeking designation of Easiform houses under the Housing Defects Act 1984.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05030"><member>Mr. John Patten</member>: I have received three such representations this year, including that from my hon. Friend the Member for Bury, South. In response I have explained that the Department has no evidence at present to justify national designation of Easiform houses under the Housing Defects Act.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05031">Mr. Sumberg asked the Secretary of State for the Environment how many local authorities have designated Easiform houses under section 12 of the Housing Defects Act 1984.</p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05032"><member>Mr. John Patten</member>: None.
<table type="span">
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="right"><i>1980&#x2013;81 &#x00A3;</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>1981&#x2013;82 &#x00A3;</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>1982&#x2013;83 &#x00A3;</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>1983&#x2013;84 &#x00A3;</i></td>
<td align="right"><i>1984&#x2013;85 &#x00A3;</i></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rugby Football Union</td>
<td align="right">21,615</td>
<td align="right">19,766</td>
<td align="right">24,703</td>
<td align="right">32,229</td>
<td align="right">23,762</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rugby Football Schools Union</td>
<td align="right">7,961</td>
<td align="right">5,161</td>
<td align="right">12,500</td>
<td align="right">6,691</td>
<td align="right">6,691</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TOTAL</td>
<td align="right">29,576</td>
<td align="right">24,927</td>
<td align="right">37,203</td>
<td align="right">38,920</td>
<td align="right">30,453</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
<p id="S6CV0089P0-05033">Figures for capital grants are only available for the last two financial years. For 1983&#x2013;84 the total was &#x00A3;137,776, and for 1984&#x2013;85,&#x00A3;183,951.</p>
</body>
</section>
</group>
</writtenanswers>
