<housecommons>
<image src="S5CV0225P0I0006"/>
<col>1</col>
<title>HOUSE OF COMMONS.</title>
<date format="1929-02-11">Monday, 11th February, 1929.</date>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00174"><i>The House met at a quarter before Three of the Clock,</i> Mr. SPEAKER <i>in the Chair.</i></p>
<debates>
<section>
<title>PRIVATE BUSINESS.</title>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00175">Great Western Railway (Air Transport) Bill (by Order),</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00176">London and North Eastern Railway (Air Transport) Bill (by Order),</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00177">London, Midland and Scottish Railway (Air Transport) Bill (by Order),</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00178">Southern Railway (Air Transport) Bill (by Order),</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00179">Second Reading deferred till Friday.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>SALFORD CORPORATION BILL,</title>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00180">"to restrict competition by omnibuses with tramway services of the Mayor, Aldermen, and Citizens of the city of Salford; to confer upon them borrowing and other financial powers; and for other purposes," presented, and read the First time: and ordered to be read a Second time.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (MIDDLESBROUGH EXTENSION) BILL,</title>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00181">"to confirm a Provisional Order of the Minister of Health relating to Middles-
<col>2</col>
brough," presented by Mr. Chamberlain; read the First time; and to be referred to the Examiners of Petitions for Private fills, and to be printed. [Bill 51.]</p>
</section>
<oralquestions>
<title>ORAL ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS.</title>
<section>
<title>ARMY ESTIMATES, 1929.</title>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00384">Estimates presented of Effective and Non-Effective Services of the Army for the financial year 1929 [by Command]; Referred to the Committee of Supply, and to be printed.</p>
</section>
</oralquestions>
<section>
<title>NEW MEMBER. SWORN,</title>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00385">William Bennett, esquire, for Borough of Battersea (South Division).</p>
</section>
</debates>
<writtenanswers>
<title>WRITTEN ANSWERS.</title>
<group>
<title>UNEMPLOYMENT.</title>
<section>
<title>JUVENILES.</title>
<body>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00386"><member>Mr. KELLY</member> asked the Minister of Labour how many Reports have been presented by local committees in response to C.E. Circular No. 2 with schemes to deal with the employment of juveniles?</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00387"><member>Mr. BETTERTON</member>: Replies to C.E. Circular No. 2 have been received from nearly all the local committees to whom it was addressed, including all those operating in the larger industrial centres. The replies are to be considered by the National Advisory Councils for juvenile employment, but I hope shortly to publish a summary for the information of hon. Members and all interested in the problem.</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00388"><member>Mr. KELLY</member> asked the Minister of Labour the number of juveniles who were placed in employment by the Employment Exchanges in the London area during the last seven years?</p>
<image src="S5CV0225P0I0022"/>
<col>33</col>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00389"><member>Mr. BETTERTON</member>: The following table gives the information desired:</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00390">Number of Vacancies Filled by Juveniles through Employment Exchanges and Juvenile Employment Bureaux in the Greater London Area during each of the Years, 1922&#x2013;1928.</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00391"><table>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="2">Year.</td>
<td align="center">Boys.</td>
<td align="center">Girls.</td>
<td align="center">Total.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1922</td>
<td>&#x2026;</td>
<td align="right">17,572</td>
<td align="right">22,655</td>
<td align="right">40,227</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1923</td>
<td>&#x2026;</td>
<td align="right">26,074</td>
<td align="right">26,463</td>
<td align="right">52,537</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1924</td>
<td>&#x2026;</td>
<td align="right">41,970</td>
<td align="right">36,013</td>
<td align="right">77,983</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1925</td>
<td>&#x2026;</td>
<td align="right">48,219</td>
<td align="right">41,420</td>
<td align="right">89,639</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1926</td>
<td>&#x2026;</td>
<td align="right">45,725</td>
<td align="right">39,627</td>
<td align="right">85,352</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1927</td>
<td>&#x2026;</td>
<td align="right">53,141</td>
<td align="right">45,290</td>
<td align="right">98,431</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1928</td>
<td>&#x2026;</td>
<td align="right">58,978</td>
<td align="right">48,992</td>
<td align="right">107,970</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00392"><member>Mr. KELLY</member> asked the Minister of Labour the number of unemployment insurance books exchanged by boys and girls of 16 to 18 years of age in the London area during 1925, 1926, 1927 and 1928?</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00393"><member>Mr. BETTERTON</member>: The following table shows for the insurance years July to June, 1925&#x2013;1928, and for the period July, 1928, to December, 1928, the number of unemployment books exchanged in the area of Greater London in respect of insured persons who were aged 16 and under 18 at the date of exchange.</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00394"><table>
<tr>
<td align="center">Period.</td>
<td align="center">Boys.</td>
<td align="center">Girls.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>July, 1925, to June, 1926</td>
<td align="center">105,519</td>
<td align="center">87,859</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>July, 1926, to June, 1927</td>
<td align="center">105,166</td>
<td align="center">89,022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>July, 1927, to June, 1928</td>
<td align="center">105,910</td>
<td align="center">90,625</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>July, 1928 to December, 1928</td>
<td align="center">108,816</td>
<td align="center">94,523</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>TRAINING, LONDON.</title>
<body>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00395"><member>Mr. KELLY</member> asked the Minister of Labour when the London unemployment training centre was closed and the reason for closing this centre?</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00396"><member>Mr. BETTERTON</member>: There has never been an adult training centre in London. For some years prior to 17th February, 1928, there were juvenile unemployment centres, but the last of these was closed on that date owing to the small numbers in attendance.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>TRANSFER OF WORKERS.</title>
<body>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00397"><member>Mr. LAWSON</member> asked the Minister of Labour the total number of miners who
<col>34</col>
have been found work under the transfer scheme and under the special arrangements with local authorities?</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00398"><member>Mr. BETTERTON</member>: According to the latest information available, the number of adult men from depressed areas who have been placed in employment in other districts through employment exchange machinery since the Prime Minister's appeal, is 10,701.</p>
</body>
</section>
</group>
</writtenanswers>
<debates>
<section>
<image src="S5CV0225P0I0038"/>
<col>65</col>
<title>ORDERS OF THE DAY.</title>
<section>
<title>SUPPLY.</title>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00526">Considered in Committee.</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00527" align="center">[Mr. DENNIS HERBERT in the Chair.]</p>
<section>
<title>CIVIL ESTIMATES, SUPPLEMENTARY<lb/> ESTIMATES, 1928.</title>
<section>
<title>CLASS V.</title>
<section>
<title>MINISTRY OF LABOUR.</title>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00528">Motion made, and Question proposed,
<quote>"That a Supplementary sum, not exceeding &#x00A3;366,000, he granted to His Majesty, to defray the Charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1929, for the Salaries and Expenses of the Ministry of Labour and Subordinate Departments, including the Exchequer Contribution to the Unemployment Fund, Grants to Associations, Local Education Authorities and others under the Unemployment Insurance, Labour Exchanges, and other Acts; Expenses of the Industrial Court; Contribution towards the Expenses of the International Labour Organisation (League of Nations); Expenses of Training and Transference of Workpeople within Great Britain and Oversea: and sundry services, including services arising out of the war."</quote></p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00701"><i>The remaining orders were read, and postponed.</i></p>
</section>
<section>
<title>ADJOURNMENT.</title>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00702">Resolved, "That this House do now adjourn."&#x2014;[<i>Commander Eyres Monsell.</i>]</p>
<p id="S5CV0225P0-00703">Adjourned accordingly at Twelve Minutes after Eleven o'Clock.</p>
</section>
</section>
</debates>
</housecommons>